<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>About TEI Rails</title>

	<author>Leitgebj, Justin</author>

      </titleStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
	<publisher>Justin S. Leitgeb</publisher>
	<pubPlace>Buffalo, NY</pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
	<p>http://teirails.phq.org</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart>About TEI Rails</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    
    <body>
      <div n="Intro">
	<head>Introduction</head>
	<p>
	  TEI Rails is a content management system for documents
	  encoded in TEI.  It is written in Ruby on Rails.
	  Development funding for the project came from a grant from
	  the National Endowment for the Humanities at the <ref
	  target="http://www.buffalo.edu"> University at
	  Buffalo</ref>.  The content management system is intended to
	  run the <ref target="http://litgloss.buffalo.edu">Litgloss
	  archive</ref>, which is a collection of texts in a variety
	  of languages which are annotated for pedagogical purposes.
	</p>
      </div>

      <div n="Features">
	<head>Features</head>

	<p>
	  TEI Rails has a number of features which make storing and
	  collaborating on documents encoded in TEI easier.  These
	  features include support for document versioning, media file
	  storage with associated documents, a workflow which
	  facilitates collaboration, and advanced features for
	  document annotation.
	</p>

	<p>
	  TEI Rails supports document versioning.  The system stores
	  all versions created of a particular document, and
	  authorized users may revert to previous versions at any
	  time.
	</p>
	
	<p>
	  The system also supports a hierarchy of users and workflow
	  for collaboration.  Without customization, the default
	  hierarchy allows for classes of users considered to be
	  system administrators, editors, contributors, and normal
	  users.
	</p>

	<p>
	  TEI Rails allows for users to collaborate on documents by
	  creating private "clones" of those documents.  A clone is
	  basically a shallow copy of a document into a private
	  workspace of a user.  Once a user and editor are satisfied
	  with her changes, an editor may pull from these local
	  changes and modify the public content item.  This approach to 
	  document workflow, which allows for "clusters" of document 
	  clones around a central document object, allows for a secure 
	  system while also providing a "sandbox" where users less familiar
	  with TEI may try their changes safely.
	</p>

	<p>
	  Multiple forms of "annotation" are supported.  TEI Rails
	  supports many forms of document markup.  Of course,
	  annotations may be made to a document according to the TEI
	  guidelines for P5 and the TEI Lite DTD.  In addition to
	  this, TEI Rails includes a web-based editor which
	  automatically inserts "annotations" which show up on a
	  rendered page with a javascript popup.  These are handy fo
	  allowing users to add notes to a document with a particular
	  knowledge of TEI or XML.
	</p>

	<p>
	  TEI Rails also includes an Annotea server, which allows for
	  collaboration on documents through XPointer references to
	  any rendered document in the TEI Rails system.  This Annotea
	  server was written as a Ruby on Rails plugin, and is shipped
	  by default with TEI Rails installations.  It is also
	  available by itself for simple inclusion in other Ruby on
	  Rails applications.
	</p>

	<p>
	  TEI Rails supports image and audio uploads to be associated
	  with content items and "litglosses" (the document markup tag
	  mentioned above).  
	</p>

	<p>
	  Finally, TEI Rails checks all input against a DTD for TEI
	  Lite, and it passes errors from the validator to the user.
	  No data are saved in the system if a document is not
	  well-formed and able to be validated against a DTD.
	</p>
      </div>

      <div n="License">
	<head>License</head>
	
	<p>
	  All of the source code for TEI Rails is available under the
	  GPLv3, which means that for most purposes it can be adapted
	  and modified freely, and that the source code is available
	  for download and distribution.
	</p>
      </div>

      <div n="Author">
	<head>Author</head>
	<p>
	  TEI Rails was written by Justin S. Leitgeb.  He may be
	  contacted with questions or comments about the program at
	  leitgebj AT hcoop DOT net.
	</p>
      </div>
    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
