<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
  <teiHeader>
    <fileDesc>
      <titleStmt>
	<title>What is Enlightenment?</title>

	<author>Foucault, Michel</author>

	<respStmt>
	  <resp>Converted to TEI by</resp>
	  <name>Justin S. Leitgeb</name>
	</respStmt>
      </titleStmt>

      <publicationStmt>
	<publisher>Unknown</publisher>
	<pubPlace>France</pubPlace>
      </publicationStmt>

      <sourceDesc>
	<p>www.foucault.info</p>
      </sourceDesc>
    </fileDesc>

    <profileDesc>
      <langUsage>
	<language ident="en-US">en-US</language>
      </langUsage>
    </profileDesc>

  </teiHeader>

  <text>
    <front>
      <titlePage>
        <docTitle>
          <titlePart>What is Enlightenment?</titlePart>
        </docTitle>
      </titlePage>
    </front>
    
    <body>
      
      <p>
	Today when a periodical asks its readers a question, it
	does so in order to collect opinions on some subject about
	which everyone has an opinion already; there is not much
	likelihood of learning anything new. In the eighteenth
	century, editors preferred to question the public on
	problems that did not yet have solutions. I don't know
	whether or not that practice was more effective; it was
	unquestionably more entertaining.
      </p>



    <p>In any event, in line with this custom, in November 1784 a
    German periodical, Berlinische Monatschrift published a response
    to the question: Was ist Aufklärung? And the respondent was
    Kant.</p>

    <p>
      A minor text, perhaps. But it seems to me that it marks the
      discreet entrance into the history of thought of a question that
      modern philosophy has not been capable of answering, but that it
      has never managed to get rid of, either. And one that has been
      repeated in various forms for two centuries now. From Hegel
      through Nietzsche or Max Weber to Horkheimer or Habermas, hardly
      any philosophy has failed to confront this same question,
      directly or indirectly. What, then, is this event that is called
      the Aufklärung and that has determined, at least in part, what
      we are, what we think, and what we do today ? Let us imagine
      that the Berlinische Monatschrift still exists and that it is
      asking its readers the question: What is modern philosophy ?
      Perhaps we could respond with an echo: modern philosophy is the
      philosophy that is attempting to answer the question raised so
      imprudently two centuries ago: Was ist Aufklärung?
    </p>

    
    <p>Let us linger a few moments over Kant's text. It merits attention for several reasons.</p>

    <list type="ordered">

      <item>To this same question, Moses Mendelssohn had also replied
      in the same journal, just two months earlier. But Kant had not
      seen Mendelssohn's text when he wrote his. To be sure, the
      encounter of the German philosophical movement with the new
      development of Jewish culture does not date from this precise
      moment. Mendelssohn had been at that crossroads for thirty years
      or so, in company with Lessing. But up to this point it had been
      a matter of making a place for Jewish culture within German
      thought -- which Lessing had tried to do in Die Juden -- or else
      of identifying problems common to Jewish thought and to German
      philosophy; this is what Mendelssohn had done in his Phadon;
      oder, Über die Unsterblichkeit der Seele. With the two texts
      published in the Berlinische Monatschrift the German Aufklärung
      and the Jewish Haskala recognize that they belong to the same
      history; they are seeking to identify the common processes from
      which they stem. And it is perhaps a way of announcing the
      acceptance of a common destiny -- we now know to what drama that
      was to lead.</item>

      <item>But there is more. In itself and within the
      Christian tradition, Kant's text poses a new problem.

      <list type="bulleted">
	<item>The present may be represented as belonging to a certain
	era of the world, distinct from the others through some
	inherent characteristics, or separated from the others by some
	dramatic event. Thus, in Plato's Statesman the interlocutors
	recognize that they belong to one of those revolutions of the
	world in which the world is turning backwards, with all the
	negative consequences that may ensue.</item>
	

	<item>The present may be interrogated in an attempt to
	decipher in it the heralding signs of a forthcoming
	event. Here we have the principle of a kind of historical
	hermeneutics of which Augustine might provide an
	example.</item>
	  
	<item>The present may also be analyzed as a point of
	transition toward the dawning of a new world. That is what
	Vico describes in the last chapter of La Scienza Nuova; what
	he sees 'today' is 'a complete humanity ... spread abroad
	through all nations, for a few great monarchs rule over this
	world of peoples'; it is also 'Europe ... radiant with such
	humanity that it abounds in all the good things that make for
	the happiness of human life.'</item>
      </list>

      <p>Now the way Kant poses the question of Aufklärung is entirely
      different: it is neither a world era to which one belongs, nor
      an event whose signs are perceived, nor the dawning of an
      accomplishment. Kant defines Aufklärung in an almost entirely
      negative way, as an Ausgang, an 'exit,' a 'way out.' In his
      other texts on history, Kant occasionally raises questions of
      origin or defines the internal teleology of a historical
      process. In the text on Aufklärung, he deals with the question
      of contemporary reality alone. He is not seeking to understand
      the present on the basis of a totality or of a future
      achievement. He is looking for a difference: What difference
      does today introduce with respect to yesterday ?</p>

      </item>
    </list>

    </body>
  </text>
</TEI>
